<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>security on Mark&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://mlavi.github.io/tags/security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in security on Mark&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 16:56:47 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mlavi.github.io/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why You Want Google Authenticator, but Don&#39;t Need It</title>
      <link>https://mlavi.github.io/post/dynamic-passwords-topt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 16:56:47 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlavi.github.io/post/dynamic-passwords-topt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two factor authentication is an important safeguard for all of your accounts and it has proven itself by protecting one of the largest software engineering organizations in the world from breach. In order to easily control your safety and privacy without resorting to cloud service providers, let&amp;rsquo;s explore how to adopt dynamic passwords and avoid outsourcing your credentials!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSH Key Authentication Overview</title>
      <link>https://mlavi.github.io/post/ssh-key-authentication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 12:46:39 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlavi.github.io/post/ssh-key-authentication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For those of you new to automation, it can be overwhelming on first
exposure to handle every link in the chain to launch your first Nutanix Calm blueprint. Many Calm Marketplace blueprints leverage Linux, cloud-init, and SSH keypairs to enable security best-practices for composable infrastructure as code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Declarative Operating Systems</title>
      <link>https://mlavi.github.io/post/declarative_os/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2016 15:44:02 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mlavi.github.io/post/declarative_os/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new breed of operating systems adopt declarative configuration management for
an interesting hybrid! OS maintenance of long-lived servers remains a challenge
for our &amp;ldquo;mutable&amp;rdquo; infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
