<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Career on Mark&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://mlavi.github.io/tags/career/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Career on Mark&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 14:11:47 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://mlavi.github.io/tags/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About Mark</title>
      <link>http://mlavi.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 14:11:47 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mlavi.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A DevOps professional with pioneering work on the world&amp;rsquo;s biggest Internet real-time event
 and web sites from an engineering, operations, content, and marketing perspective.
 My focus is on people and software development along with system design thinking for the
 whole life cycle: I can build, grow, and manage teams, applications, networks, and servers
 to work together while planning and nurturing their continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark first touched the Internet in 1991 when he was sponsored to do undergraduate research.
 After graduation and Internet withdrawal, he joined the first national commercial Internet
 Service Provider (before the world wide web).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the web masters of Netscape, cnnfn.com, and sgi.com, Mark was part of the
 world&amp;rsquo;s largest and earliest media and web sites. Mark progressed to Developer
 Relations, where he became the JavaScript and LDAP Technology Evangelist.
One compliment: &amp;ldquo;Mark is an engineer who can speak&amp;rdquo; captures his ability to relate technical
 subjects to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark&amp;rsquo;s approach mixes software engineering disciplines with art and operations, embracing
 Internet architecture, real-time media, and the ability to nurture people, developers,
 networks, and systems to work together. His multidisciplinary practice is complimented
 by the term &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps&#34;&gt;DevOps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can review Mark&amp;rsquo;s career and endorsements at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/marklavi&#34;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/marklavi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>