<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bootstrap on Mark&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://mark.lavi.us/tags/bootstrap/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bootstrap on Mark&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 09:37:33 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://mark.lavi.us/tags/bootstrap/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Learning AlpineLinux.org, Ansible.com, and Packer.io</title>
      <link>http://mark.lavi.us/post/learning-alpine-linux-ansible-and-packer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 09:37:33 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mark.lavi.us/post/learning-alpine-linux-ansible-and-packer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For my 2020-1 holiday break, I decided my next personal project would be to rebuild my home infrastructure on containers. I&amp;rsquo;d been inspired by a recent discovery of &lt;a href=&#34;https://linuxserver.io&#34;&gt;LinuxServer.io&lt;/a&gt;, where open source projects are built and run as containers. While I have a burning desire to better my Kubernetes practice, not enough of the world delivers software as a Helm chart, so merely running everything as containers would be a good intermediate step. Let me share my first six steps with examples&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DevOps in a Box</title>
      <link>http://mark.lavi.us/post/devops-in-a-box/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 May 2018 13:42:39 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mark.lavi.us/post/devops-in-a-box/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My long time fantasy has been to demonstrate an entire CI/CD pipeline with
continuous operations of applications to discuss behavior driven operations
and testing as monitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The call for this happened over and over at DevOpsDays to answer: how does one
learn DevOps, practice site reliability engineering, or have a full
application lifecycle environment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s create a minimal viable product &lt;a href=&#34;../devops-btd-pattern&#34;&gt;BTD scenario&lt;/a&gt;
of my &lt;a href=&#34;../devops-automation&#34;&gt;DevOps Automation&lt;/a&gt; system,
extend it to prefix Governance and suffix Management,
and then drive maturity to illustrate and discuss best practices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
