<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cms on Mark&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://mlavi.github.io/tags/cms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cms on Mark&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 14:11:47 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://mlavi.github.io/tags/cms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Time for a new development project!</title>
      <link>http://mlavi.github.io/post/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 14:11:47 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://mlavi.github.io/post/first/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Embarking on a new adventure is always the best time in a project because all your dreams
 are possible! You research your ideas, find new tools and libraries, and smell the fresh
 scent of unhindered development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;then-you-start:e8fb9c67eba912c72729806db31eaa1b&#34;&gt;Then you start&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You find that your idea is broad and multi-faceted, tools are in various states of acceptable
 use and documentation, and there is a bevy of dependencies: each representing a small
 landscape to conquer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-sink-into-reality:e8fb9c67eba912c72729806db31eaa1b&#34;&gt;&amp;hellip; to sink into reality!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original title of this first post was &amp;ldquo;Time for a new Blog&amp;rdquo; to document my experiment
 with Github Pages, Jekyll, and Hugo: it has been a fascinating study in scope creep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m prototyping, so it&amp;rsquo;s all good, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll update later with how I&amp;rsquo;ve navigated the static web site blog quest, thus far it has been an
 exercise in transferring most of the standard content management system functionality into
 smaller tools and libraries which inverts the workflow. I think the journey will be worth
 it because I&amp;rsquo;ve caught glimpses which validate this approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can blog from the command line and presumably anywhere (including my phone) with some setup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can test the build of my content, templates, and enhanced work on those elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything under revision control, therefore: blog + content = testable software!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I&amp;rsquo;ve accomplished much with Joomla, WordPress, Drupal, and ModX over the years,
 you inevitably fall out of love after the first month with complex and brittle software.
 Will it happen again?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>